I'm going to start by asking you a question:
سوف أبدأ المحادثة بسؤال أطرحه عليكم:
Is anyone familiar with the blue algae problem?
هل يعلم أيّ منكم بمشكلة الطحالب الزرقاء؟
Okay, so most of you are.
حسنا، معظمكم يعلم.
I think we can all agree it's a serious issue.
أظنّ أنّ بامكاننا جميعا أن نتفقّ على كونها مشكلة كبيرة.
Nobody wants to drink blue algae-contaminated water,
ما من أحد يرغب في شرب مياه ملوّثة بالطحالب الزرقاء،
or swim in a blue algae-infested lake.
أو السباحة في بحيرة موبوءة بها.
Right?
أليس كذلك؟
I hope you won't be disappointed,
أتمنّى أن لا يخيب أملكم،
but today, I won't be talking about blue algae.
لكنني اليوم لن أتحدّث عن الطحالب الّزرقاء.
Instead, I'll be talking about the main cause
بل سأتحدّث عن السبب الرّئيسي
at the root of this issue,
لجزور هذه المشكلة،
which I will be referring to as the phosphorus crisis.
و التي سأسمّيها بأزمة الفوسفور.
Why have I chosen to talk to you about the phosphorus crisis today?
لماذا اخترت أن أتحدّث معكم اليوم عن أزمة الفوسفور؟
For the simple reason that nobody else is talking about it.
لسبب بسيط و هو أنّ ما من أحد يتحدّث عنها.
And by the end of my presentation, I hope that the general public
و بنهاية هذه المحادثة، أتمنّى أن يكون الرأي العام
will be more aware of this crisis and this issue.
أكثر وعيا بهذه الأزمة و المشكلة.
Now, the problem is that if I ask,
الان ، إن طرحت عليكم سؤالا:
why do we find ourselves in this situation with blue algae?
لماذا وجدنا أنفسنا في هذا الموقف مع الطحالب الزرقاء؟
The answer is that it comes from how we farm.
الإجابة ستكون: بسبب طريقتنا في الزّراعة.
We use fertilizers in our farming, chemical fertilizers.
نحن نستعمل الأسمدة في الزراعة، الأسمدة الكيميائية.
Why do we use chemical fertilizers in agriculture?
لماذا نقوم باستعمال الأسمدة الكيميائية في الزراعة؟
Basically, to help plants grow and to produce a better yield.
بالأساس نقوم بذلك لمساعدة النباتات على النّمو و للحصول على إنتاجية أفضل.
The issue is that this is set to engender
إنّه أمر سيسبّب خطرا
an environmental problem that is without precedent.
بيئيّا لا مثيل له.
Before going further, let me give you a crash course in plant biology.
قبل الحديث دعوني أعطيكم دورة مكثفة في علم الأحياء النباتية.
So, what does a plant need in order to grow?
فما الذي تحتاجه النّبتة للنّمو؟
A plant, quite simply, needs light, it needs CO2,
النّبتة ببساطه تحتاج، الضوء و ثاني أكسيد الكربون،
but even more importantly, it needs nutrients,
لكن أيضا ما أهمّ من ذلك، تحتاج المغذّيات،
which it draws from the soil.
التي تمتصّها من التّربة.
Several of these nutrients are essential chemical elements:
العديد من هذه المغذّيات هي عناصر كيميائية أساسيّة:
phosphorus, nitrogen and calcium.
الفسفور، النيتروجين و الكالسيوم.
So, the plant’s roots will extract these resources.
إذن تقوم جذور النّبتة باستخراج هذه العناصر.
Today I'll be focusing on a major problem that is linked to phosphorus.
سأركّز اليوم على مشكل كبيره ترتبط بالفوسفور.
Why phosphorus in particular?
لماذا الفسفور بالذّات؟
Because it is the most problematic chemical element.
لأنّه أكثر العناصر الكيميائية اشكاليّة.
By the end of my presentation, you will have seen
عند نهاية محادثتي، سوف تكونون قد رأيتم
what these problems are, and where we are today.
ماهيّة هذه المشاكل و أين نحن منها اليوم.
Phosphorus is a chemical element
الفوسفور هو عنصر كيميائيّ
that is essential to life. This is a very important point.
أساسيّ للحياة. وهذه نقطة في غاية الأهميّة.
I’d like everyone to understand precisely what the phosphorus issue is.
أرغب من الجميع أن يفهم بدقّة ماهي مشكلة الفوسفور.
Phosphorus is a key component in several molecules,
الفوسفور هو مكوّن أساسيّ في العديد من الجزيئات،
in many of our molecules of life.
جزيئات الحياة الخاصة بنا.
Experts in the field will know
الخبراء بالمجال يعلمون أنّ
that cellular communication is phosphorus-based --
التّواصل الخلويّ يستند على الفوسفور،
phosphorylation, dephosphorylation.
عمليّة الفسفرة و عكسها.
Cell membranes are phosphorus-based: These are called phospholipids.
الأغشية الخلوية تتكوّن من الفوسفور: تسمّى الدّهون الفسفوريّة.
The energy in all living things, ATP, is phosphorus-based.
الطاقة الموجودة بكلّ الكائنات الحيّة، ثلاثي فوسفات الأدينوسين متكوّن من الفوسفور.
And more importantly still, phosphorus is a key component of DNA,
و الأهمّ من كلّ هذا، الفوسفور هو مكوّن أساسيّ للحمض النووي،
something everyone is familiar with, and which is shown in this image.
وهو أمر يعلمه الكثيرون، وترونه هذا في هذه الصّورة.
DNA is our genetic heritage.
الحمض النووي هو إرثنا الجينيّ.
It is extremely important, and once again, phosphorus is a key player.
إنّه في غاية الأهميّة، الفوسفور هو عنصر أساسيّ.
Now, where do we find this phosphorus?
لكن أين يوجد الفوسفور؟
As humans, where do we find it?
كبشر، أين يمكننا إيجاده؟
As I explained earlier,
كما كنت قد فسّرت سابقا،
plants extract phosphorus from the soil, through water.
النّباتات تقوم باستخراج الفوسفور من التّربة، عبر الماء.
So, we humans get it from the things we eat:
إذن نحن البشر نحصل عليه من خلال ما نأكله:
plants, vegetables, fruits,
النّباتات و الخضروات و الغلال
and also from eggs, meat and milk.
و أيضا من البيض و اللّحم و الحليب.
It’s true that some humans eat better than others.
صحيح أنّ بعض البشر يأكلون أفضل من غيرهم.
Some are happier than others.
بعضهم أسعد من بعض.
And now, looking at this picture, which speaks for itself,
و الآن، بالنّظر إلى هذه الصورة التي تتحدّث عن نفسها،
we see modern agriculture,
نحن نرى الزراعة العصريّة،
which I also refer to as intensive agriculture.
و التي أسمّيها أيضا الزّراعة المكثّفة.
Intensive agriculture is based on the use of chemical fertilizers.
الزّراعة المكثّفة ترتكز على استعمال الأسمدة الكيميائية.
Without them, we would not manage to produce enough
من دونها، نحن لا نستطيع الانتاج كفاية
to feed the world's population.
لتغذية سكان العالم.
Speaking of humans, there are currently 7 billion of us on Earth.
بالحديث عن البشر، هناك 7 مليارات نسمة منّا.
In less than 40 years, there will be 9 billion of us.
في أقل من 40 سنوات، سيكون هناك أكثر من 9 مليارات منّا.
And the question is a simple one: Do we have enough phosphorus
و السؤال البسيط الذي يطرح هو: هل لدينا ما يكفي من الفوسفور
to feed our future generations?
لتغذية الأجيال المستقبلية؟
So, in order to understand these issues, where do we find our phosphorus?
من أجل فهم هذه المشاكل، أين نجد الفوسفور؟
Let me explain.
دعوني أفسّر.
But first, let’s just suppose
لكن في البدأ، دعونا نفترض
that we are using 100 percent of a given dose of phosphorus.
أنّّنا نستخدم 100% من جرعة كاملة من الفوسفور.
Only 15 percent of this 100 percent goes to the plant. Eighty-five percent is lost.
فقط 15% من تلك الكمية تذهب إلى النّبتة. تتمّ خسارة 85% منها.
It goes into the soil, ending its journey in the lakes,
إنّها تعود إلى التّربة، منهية رحلتها في البحيرات،
resulting in lakes with extra phosphorus, which leads to the blue algae problem.
منتجة بحيرات ذات كمية إضافية من الفوسفور، وهو ما يؤدّي إلى مشكلة الطحالب الزرقاء.
So, you’ll see there’s a problem here, something that is illogical.
تستطيعون معرفة أنّ هناك مشكلا ما هنا، هناك أمر غير منطقيّ.
A hundred percent of the phosphorus is used, but only 15 percent goes to the plant.
يتم استعمال 100% من الفوسفور لكن 15% فقط يذهب إلى النّبتة.
You’re going to tell me it’s wasteful.
ستقولون أنّ تلك خسارة.
Yes, it is. What is worse is that it is very expensive.
نعم، بالفعل. و الأسوأ في الأمر أنّه مكلف جدّا.
Nobody wants to throw their money out the window,
ما من أحد يرغب في "رمي أموالهم من النّافذة"،
but unfortunately that's what is happening here.
لكن للأسف هذا ما يحدث بالفعل.
Eighty percent of each dose of phosphorus is lost.
تتمّ خسارة 80% من كلّ جرعة فوسفور.
Modern agriculture depends on phosphorus.
الزّراعة العصرية تعتمد على الفوسفور.
And because in order to get 15 percent of it to the plant, all the rest is lost,
و بما أنّ الحصول على 15% منه للنّبتة يتطلّب خسارة الكمية الباقية،
we have to add more and more.
فنحن نحتاج إلى إضافة المزيد و المزيد.
Now, where will we get this phosphorus from?
لكن من أين سنحصل على الفوسفور؟
Basically, we get it out of mines.
نحن نجده في الأساس بالمناجم.
This is the cover of an extraordinary article
هذا عنوان لمقال رائع
published in Nature in 2009,
نشر في دورية نايتشر سنة 2009،
which really launched the discussion about the phosphorus crisis.
وهو ما بدأ الجدل حول أزمة الفوسفور.
Phosphorus, a nutrient essential to life, which is becoming increasingly scarce,
الفوسفور الذي هو مغذّ أساسيّ للحياة، تتزايد ندرته بصفة متصاعدة
yet nobody is talking about it.
لكن ما من أحد يتحدّث عن الأمر.
And everyone agrees: Politicians and scientists are in agreement
و الكلّ متفق، العلماء و السياسيون يتفقون
that we are headed for a phosphorus crisis.
على كوننا متّجهين صوب أزمة في الفوسفور.
What you are seeing here is an open-pit mine in the U.S.,
ما نراه هنا هو منجم سطحيّ في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
and to give you an idea of the dimensions of this mine,
و لإعطائكم فكرة عن أبعاد هذا المنجم،
if you look in the top right-hand corner, the little crane you can see,
إن نظرتم إلى الجهة اليمنى العلوية، ذلك المرفاع الصغير الذين ترونه
that is a giant crane.
هو في الواقع كبير الحجم.
So that really puts it into perspective.
هذا يضع الأمور في نصابها.
So, we get phosphorus from mines.
إذن فنحن نستخرج الفوسفور من المناجم.
And if I make a comparison with oil,
و إن قمت بمقارنة مع النّفط،
there’s an oil crisis, we talk about it, we talk about global warming,
فهناك أزمة نفطيّة، نحن نتحدّث عنها، و نتحدّث عن الاحتباس الحراري
yet we never mention the phosphorus crisis.
لكننا لا نذكر أبدا أزمة الفوسفور.
To come back to the oil problem, oil is something we can replace.
عودة لأزمة النّفط، فالنّفط أمر يمكننا استبداله.
We can use biofuels, or solar power,
نستطيع استعمال الوقود الحيوي أو الطاقة الشمسية،
or hydropower, but phosphorus is an essential element,
أو الطاقة المائية، لكن الفوسفور عنصر أساسي
indispensable to life, and we can’t replace it.
ضروري للحياة و لا يمكن استبداله.
What is the current state of the world's phosphorus reserves?
ماهو وضع الحاليّ لمخزون العالميّ للفوسفور؟
This graph gives you a rough idea of where we are today.
هذا الرسم البيانيّ يعطيكم فكرة قاسية عن وضعه حاليّا.
The black line represents predictions for phosphorus reserves.
الخط الأسود يمثّل التنبؤات عن مخزون الفوسفور.
In 2030, we’ll reach the peak.
بحلول سنة 2030، سوف نصل إلى القمة.
By the end of this century, it will all be gone.
مع نهاية القرن، سيكون قد اختفى كله.
The dotted line shows where we are today.
المستقيم المنقّط يمثّل وضعيتنا الحالية.
As you can see, they meet in 2030, I’ll be retired by then.
كما ترون، الخطان يلتقيان في سنة 2030، سأكون قد تقاعدت وقتها.
But we are indeed heading for a major crisis,
لكننا بالفعل متّجهون نحو أزمة كبرى
and I’d like people to become aware of this problem.
و أرغب في جعل النّاس أكثر وعيا بالأمر.
Do we have a solution?
هل هناك حلّ؟
What are we to do? We are faced with a paradox.
ما الذي يمكننا فعله؟ نحن في مواجهة مفارقة.
Less and less phosphorus will be available.
سيكون هناك كميات متناقصة من الفوسفور
By 2050 there will be 9 billion of us,
و بحلول سنة 2050 سيكون عددنا 9 مليارات
and according to the U.N. Food and Agriculture Organization,
و وفقا لمنظمة الأغذية والزراعة،
we will need to produce twice as much food in 2050 than we do today.
سوف نحتاج إلى انتاج ضعف كمية الطعام في سنة 2050 مقارنة باليوم.
So, we will have less phosphorus, but we'll need to produce more food.
إذن سيكون هناك أقل فوسفور لكن سنحتاج إلى انتاج طعام أكثر.
What should we do?
ماذا يجب علينا فعله؟
It truly is a paradoxical situation.
إنّها بالفعل مفارقة.
Do we have a solution, or an alternative
هل يوجد هناك حلّ أو بديل
which will allow us to optimize phosphorus use?
سيمكّننا من تحسين استعمال الفوسفور؟
Remember that 80 percent is destined to be lost.
تذكّروا أنّ 80% خسارتها محتومة.
The solution I'm offering today is one that has existed for a very long time,
الحل الذي أقدّمه اليوم هو حلّ كان دائما موجودا منذ زمن طويل،
even before plants existed on Earth,
حتّى قبل وجود النّباتات على الأرض،
and it's a microscopic mushroom that is very mysterious,
إنّه فطر مجهريّ في غاية الغموض،
very simple, and yet also extremely complex.
في غاية البساطة لكن أيضا في غاية التّعقيد.
I've been fascinated by this little mushroom for over 16 years now.
لقد بهرني هذا الفطر الصغير و لا يزال يبهرني منذ 16 سنة مضت.
It has led me to further my research
لقد قادني للتقدم في بحثي
and to use it as a model for my laboratory research.
و استعمال نموذج لمختبر أبحاثي.
This mushroom exists in symbiosis with the roots.
هذا الفطر يتعايش مع الجذور.
By symbiosis, I mean a bidirectional and mutually beneficial association
و بالتعايش، أنا أقصد التّرابط الثنائي و المشترك
which is also called mycorrhiza.
وهو ما يسمّى بالجذريات فطرية.
This slide illustrates the elements of a mycorrhiza.
هذا الرّسم يكشف عن عناصر الجذريات فطرية.
You’re looking at the root of wheat,
أنتم تنظرون إلى جذر قمح
one of the world’s most important plants.
وهي إحدى أهم النباتات في العالم.
Normally, a root will find phosphorus all by itself.
في العادة، سيقوم الجذر بالعثور على الفوسفور بنفسه.
It will go in search of phosphorus,
سوف يحاول البحث عن الفوسفور،
but only within the one millimeter which surrounds it.
لكن فقط في محيط الذي لا تتجاوز مساحته المليمتر الواحد.
Beyond one millimeter, the root is ineffective.
بعد نطاق المليمتر الواحد، يصبح الجذر غير فعّال.
It cannot go further in its search for phosphorus.
إنّه لا يستطيع الذهاب أبعد بحثا عن الفوسفور.
Now, imagine this tiny, microscopic mushroom.
و الآن حاولوا تخيّل هذا الفطر الضئيل الحجم.
It grows much faster,
إنّه ينمو بوتيرة أسرع بكثير،
and is much better designed to seek out phosphorus.
وهو مصمّم للبحث أفضل عن الفوسفور.
It can go beyond the root’s one-millimeter scope
إنّه قادر على تجاوز حدود الجذر التي تبلغ مليمترا واحدا
to seek out phosphorus.
و البحث عن الفوسفور.
I haven’t invented anything at all;
لم أخترع أيّ شيء أبدا،
it's a biotechnology that has existed for 450 million years.
إنّها تكنولوجيا بيولوجية موجودة منذ ما يناهز 450 مليون سنة.
And over time, this mushroom has evolved and adapted to seek out
و بمرور الزّمن، تطوّر هذا الفطر و تأقلم للبحث عن
even the tiniest trace of phosphorus, and to put it to use,
حتّى أصغر آثار الفوسفور و استعمالها
to make it available to the plant.
و جعلها متاحة للنبتة.
What you’re seeing here, in the real world, is a carrot root,
ما ترونه هنا في العالم الواقعي، هي جذور جزر،
and the mushroom with its very fine filaments.
و الفطر ذو الشعيرات الدقيقة جدا.
Looking closer, we can see that this mushroom
عند التكبير، تستطيعون رؤية أنّ هذا الفطر
is very gentle in its penetration.
رقيق جدّا أثناء تغلغله.
It will proliferate between the root's cells,
سوف ينتشر بين خلايا الجذور
eventually penetrating a cell
متغلغلا في الخلايا نفسها
and starting to form a typical arbuscular structure,
و يبدأ بتشكيل هيكل متفرّع
which will considerably increase the exchange interface
وهو ما سيقوم بتوسيع مساحة التّبادل بين
between the plant and the mushroom.
الفطر و النّبتة بصفة كبيرة.
And it is through this structure that mutual exchanges will occur.
إنّ التبادلات المشتركة تحدث من خلال هذا الهيكل.
It’s a win-win trade:
إنّه تبادل مربح للطرفين:
I give you phosphorus, and you feed me.
أنا أعطيك الفوسفور و أنت تقوم بإطعامي.
True symbiosis.
إنّه تعايش حقيقيّ.
Now let's add a mycorrhiza plant
نقوم بإضافة نبتة الجذريات الفطرية
into the diagram I used earlier.
إلى الرسم البياني الذي استخدمته سابقا.
And instead of using a 100 percent dose, I’m going to reduce it to 25 percent.
و عوض استعمال جرعة 100%، سوف أقوم بتخفيضها إلى 25%.
You’ll see that of this 25 percent, most will benefit the plant,
سوف ترون أنّ من 25% فإنّ الأغلبية سوف تنفع النّبتة،
more than 90 percent.
أكثر من 90%.
A very small amount of phosphorus will remain in the soil.
سوف تبقى كمية ضئيلة جدا من الفوسفور في التربة.
That's completely natural.
إنّه أمر طبيعيّ جدّأ.
What's more is that in certain cases, we don't even need to add phosphorus.
و في بعض الحالات، قد لا نحتاج أبدا لإضافة الفوسفور.
If you recall the graphs I showed you earlier,
إن كنتم تتذكّرون الرسم البيانيّ، فقد أريتكم سابقا
85 percent of phosphorus is lost in the soil,
أنّ 85% من الفوسفور يضيع في التّربة،
and the plants are unable to access it.
و يصبح غير متاح للنّباتات.
Even though it is present in the soil, it is in insoluble form.
حتّى لو كان موجودا في التّربة، فهو يصبح غير قابل للحل
The plant is only able to seek out soluble forms.
و النّبتة قادرة فقط على استخراج الحالات القابلة للذوبان.
The mushroom is capable of dissolving this insoluble form
أمّا الفطر فهو قادر على تحليل هذه الحالة الغير قابلة للحلّ
and making it available for the plant to use.
و جعلها متاحة للنّبتة لتستعملها.
To further support my argument, here is a picture that speaks for itself.
لمزيد دعم حجّتي، إليكم هذه الصورة التي تتحدّث عن نفسها.
These are trials in a field of sorghum.
هذه محاولات في حقل للذرة الرفيعة.
On the left side, you see the yield produced using conventional agriculture,
في الجانب الأيسر، ترون المحاصيل المنتجة باستعمال الزراعة العادية،
with a 100 percent phosphorus dose.
بجرعة 100% من الفوسفور.
On the other side, the dose was reduced to 50 percent,
و في الجانب الآخر، تمّ تخفيض الجرعة إلى 50%
and just look at the yield.
و انظروا إلى المحصول.
With only a half-dose, we achieved a better yield.
باستعمال نصف الجرعة فقط، أنتجنا محصولا أفضل.
This is to show you that this method works.
هذا دليل على أنّ هذه الطريقة فعّالة.
And in some cases, in Cuba, Mexico and India,
و في بعض الحالات بكوبا و المكسيك و الهند،
the dose can be reduced to 25 percent, and in several other cases,
تمّ تخفيض الجرعة إلى 25%، و في حالات أخرى
there's no need to add any phosphorus at all,
لم تكن هناك حاجة لإضافة الفوسفور أصلا
because the mushrooms are so well adapted
لأنّ الفطر كان متأقلما جدّا
to finding phosphorus and drawing it from the soil.
في البحث عن الفوسفور و جذبه من التربة.
This is an example of soy production in Canada.
هذا مثال على انتاج الصوجا في كندا.
Mycorrhiza was used in one field but not in the other.
تمّ استعمال الفطريات الجذرية في واحد من حقلين.
And here, where blue indicates a better yield, and yellow a weaker yield.
هنا اللون الأزرق يرمز إلى محاصيل أفضل و الأصفر محاصيل أسوأ.
The black rectangle is the plot
المستطيل الأسود هي قطعة الأرض
from which the mycorrhiza was added.
التي تمّ إضافة الفطريات الجذرية إليها.
In other words, as I already said, I have invented nothing.
كما قلت سابقا فأنا لم أخترع شيئا.
Mycorrhiza has existed for 450 million years,
الفطريات الجذرية كانت دائما موجودة منذ 450 مليون سنة،
and it has even helped modern-day plant species to diversify.
و قد ساعدت أنواع نباتات الحقبة المعاصرة في التنوع.
So, this it isn't something that is still undergoing lab tests.
إذن فهي ليست أمرا لا يزال يحتاج للتجارب المخبرية.
Mycorrhiza exists, it works,
الفطريات الجذرية موجودة و هي فعالة،
it's produced at an industrial scale and commercialized worldwide.
إنّها تصنّع على المجال الصناعيّ و تسوّق عالميّا.
The problem is that people are not aware of it.
المشكلة هي أنّ الناس لا يدركون ذلك.
People like food producers and farmers are still not aware of this problem.
الأشخاص مثل منتجي الأطعمة و الفلاحين ليسوا واعين بهذه المشكلة.
We have a technology that works,
لدينا تكنولوجيا فعّالة
and one that, if used correctly, will alleviate some of the pressure
و إن تمّ استعمالها كما يجب فقد ترفع من الضغوطات
we are putting on the world's phosphorus reserves.
التي نضعها على كاهل المخزون العالمي للفوسفور.
In conclusion, I am a scientist and a dreamer.
أخيرا، أنا عالم و حالم.
I'm passionate about this topic.
أنا متحمّس بشأن هذا الموضوع.
So if you were to ask me what my retirement dream is,
فإن سألتني عن حلم تقاعدي،
which will be at the moment we reach that phosphorus peak,
الذي سيتزامن مع وصول أزمة الفوسفور لذروتها،
it would be that we use one label, "Made with mycorrhiza,"
ستكون الإجابة أن يتمّ استعمال علامة "صنع بالجذريات فطرية"
and that my children and grandchildren
التي ستوضع بالمنتجات التي
buy products bearing that label too.
سيشتريها أبنائي و أحفادي.
Thank you for your attention.
شكرا لانتباهكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)